Ellen L. Lutz Papers MS177
Digital Collections and Archives, Tufts University
Ellen L. Lutz Papers
1960 -- 2010
1942 -- 2010
Digital Collections and Archives, Tufts University
Lutz, Ellen L.
MS177
45.89 Linear Feet 37 record cartons, 2 legal size document boxes, 1 half letter size document box, 1 oversize box, 1 oversize folder
1 Audiovisual Object(s)
255 Digital Object(s)
Arrangement
This collection is organized into eleven series: Personal files; Research materials and field investigations regarding victims of the military juntas in Uruguay, Argentina, and Chile; Human Rights Watch and American Civil Liberties Union files; Human rights litigation files; Harvard fellowship files; Fletcher and the Center for Human Rights and Conflict Resolution files; Mediation and arbitration files; Cultural Survival files; Projects and subject files; Publications, presentations, and conference files; General research materials
Scope and Contents
This collection contains research material and notes, publication drafts, correspondence, lectures, conference papers, and project files that span 1960 through 2010, documenting Ellen Lutz's life experiences and career in human rights, international law, mediation and conflict resolution. The collection includes correspondence from friends in Uruguay during the early 1970s; material regarding her travels in South America in the 1970s and 80s, particularly her work in Uruguay; photographs from her work as an election supervisor in Bosnia in 1997; photographs and itineraries from her participation in the 2003 Colombia Delegation with Congressman James McGovern; drafts and research for Cultural Survival's 2008 petition to the Inter-American Commission on Human Rights regarding human rights violations against the indigenous Ngobe tribe by the Government of Panama; and her work for Amnesty International, Human Rights Watch, Fletcher and the Center for Human Rights and Conflict Resolution, and Cultural Survival. Topics covered include reparation, torture, universal jurisdiction, accountability, democracy, human rights in Latin America, transitional justice, alternative dispute resolution, and the application of negotiation and mediation skills in human rights advocacy.
Biographical / Historical
Ellen Louise Lutz (1955-2010) devoted her life to the defense and advocacy of human rights as a prolific lawyer, teacher, writer, world traveler and activist. She worked in several positions at the Fletcher School of Law and Diplomacy from 1995 through 2004, eventually serving as Adjunct Associate Professor of Law and as Executive Director of the Center for Human Rights and Conflict Resolution (2000-2003).
Lutz's interest in human rights began in 1971-1972, when she traveled to Uruguay as a high school exchange student and witnessed the turbulent months preceding the military dictatorship. "The experience profoundly altered my life and laid the foundation of my career as a human rights lawyer and law professor," she wrote in her 1999 Fulbright application. "The military's response a year later forever altered my perception that democracy and the protection of human rights could be assumed. If such repression were possible in tiny, historically democratic Uruguay, it could happen anywhere." She received her Bachelor's Degree from Temple University in 1976 and a Master's in Anthropology from Bryn Mawr in 1978. From 1979 to 1981 she worked for Amnesty International, first as a Campaign Assistant for Latin America in Washington, D.C., and then as their Western Regional Organizer in San Francisco, CA. She earned her law degree from UC Berkeley in 1985. In 1986 and 1987 she worked as an Associate Attorney for the ACLU Foundation of Southern California. During this period, she and her first husband, Glenn Randall, advocated for legal, medical and psychological assistance for victims of torture. From 1989 to 1994, Lutz served as the California Office Director for Human Rights Watch, where she researched and publicized human and civil rights violations in Mexico and represented clients in groundbreaking human rights cases against former Philippine dictator Ferdinand Marcos and Argentine General Carlos Guillermo Suárez-Mason.
In 1994 she moved with her husband and two children to Westborough, Massachusetts, where she became involved in community initiatives, founding the Westborough Community Land Trust in 1997, serving as Chair of the Westborough Open Space Preservation Committee, and facilitating Worcester's Middle East Dialogue Group. In 1999 she partnered with Timothy Buckalew to establish Buckalew & Lutz, a Westborough firm specializing in labor and employment law, public policy, and international arbitration and mediation. Meanwhile, she continued her work in human rights as a Visiting Fellow to Harvard's Human Rights Program in 1994 and 1995. She began teaching at Tufts University in 1995, when she joined the Fletcher School as Adjunct Associate Professor of Law. In 2000 she helped establish Fletcher's Center for Human Rights and Conflict Resolution, with the mission of teaching the application of negotiation and mediation skills in human rights advocacy. While working and teaching at Tufts, she pursued other professional projects. In September of 1997, she traveled to Sarajevo, Bosnia as an International Election Supervisor for the Organization for Security and Co-operation in Europe (OSCE). Working again for Human Rights Watch, Lutz served as Delegate to the Diplomatic Conference to establish an International Criminal Court in 1998. In the summer of 1999 she traveled back to Uruguay as a Fulbright Fellow at the Universidad de la Republica Law School in Montevideo. In 2003 she joined Congressman James O. McGovern's Mission to Colombia to evaluate the impact of U.S. policy and armed conflict on Colombian civil society.
In 2004 Lutz left Tufts University for the position of Executive Director at Cultural Survival (CS). Through her work at CS, she met her future husband, Theodore (Ted) Macdonald. She worked for CS until just a few weeks before her death in 2010. In a memoriam written for Lutz on behalf of CS, the author describes her accomplishments for the organization: "She led Cultural Survival into Native American language revitalization; she started a program to submit Indigenous rights reports to the UN Human Rights Council; she launched our first on-the-ground human rights investigation in Kenya; she oversaw Cultural Survival's merger with Global Response; she helped organize congressional hearings on Indigenous rights[…] And that's the short list." Throughout her career, Lutz collaborated with other human rights advocates to publish dozens of articles and books, including the two most recent volumes, Prosecuting Heads of State (2009) and Human Rights and Conflict Resolution in Context (2009). Colleagues in the human rights community she has worked closely with include Eileen F. Babbitt, Hurst Hannum, Paul Hoffman, Caitlin Reiger, Naomi Roht-Arriaza, and Kathryn Sikkink.
Ellen Lutz passed away on November 4, 2010 at her home in Cambridge, Massachusetts.
Conditions Governing Access
This collection contains some restricted material. Restrictions related to specific material are listed in the detailed contents list.
Social justice; Human rights; International law; Lawyers; Latin America; Foreign affairs; Faculty papers; Social justice
- Personal files, 1963 -- 2009; 1963 -- 1986; MS177.001; 5.9 Linear Feet; 4 Digital Object(s)
  Scope and Contents
  This series contains personal correspondence, diaries, schoolwork, job applications and other non-professional material dating from 1963 to 2004, with the bulk of the material from 1963 to 1986. A significant portion of this series consists of correspondence with family and friends from Ellen's year as an exchange student in Uruguay in 1971-72. After her return to the United States Ellen continued her correspondence with friends in Uruguay, much of which dates from the period directly preceding and following the establishment of the military regime in 1973.
  Arrangement
  This series is arranged chronologically.
  Conditions Governing Access
  75 years from the date of creation. Open for research.
  - [Girl Scout sash, cap, patches and other material], 1963 -- 1966; MS177.001.043.00015 (Box MS177 Shared 1)
    Open for research.
    These items are located in a separate box.
  - [Sixth grade Mexico project], 1966; MS177.001.043.00016 (Box MS177 Shared 2)
    This item is oversize and located separately.
  - Autographs [book of notes from friends], 1965 -- 1969; MS177.001.043.00017 (Box MS177 Shared 3)
  - Rowe [summer camp], 1966 -- 1969; MS177.001.043.00018 (Box MS177 Shared 3)
  - [Rowe summer camp signed pillowcase], 1968; MS177.001.043.00019 (Box MS177 Shared 1)
    This item is located in a separate box.
  - Letters from Rowe, 1966 -- 1970; MS177.001.043.00020 (Box MS177 Shared 3)
  - New Light and other underground papers, 1968 -- 1969; MS177.001.043.00021 (Box MS177 Shared 3)
  - [Letters regarding high school activism], 1969 -- 1970; MS177.001.043.00022 (Box MS177 Shared 3)
  - [Diary], 1970; MS177.001.043.00023 (Box MS177 Shared 3)
  - [Encampment for Citizenship], 1970; MS177.001.043.00024 (Box MS177 Shared 3)
  - Letters from Encampment for Citizenship [1 of 3], 1970; MS177.001.043.00025 (Box MS177 Shared 3)
  - Letters from Encampment for Citizenship [2 of 3], 1970; MS177.001.043.00026 (Box MS177 Shared 3)
  - Letters from Encampment for Citizenship [3 of 3], 1970; MS177.001.043.00027 (Box MS177 Shared 3)
  - [High school concert programs], 1971; MS177.001.043.00028 (Box MS177 Shared 3)
  - Rotary [International, exchange program], 1970 -- 1972; MS177.001.044.00001 (Box 44)
  - [School notebooks from Uruguay], 1971 -- 1972; MS177.001.044.00002 (Box 44)
  - Correspondence to and from Uruguay, 1971-72 [1 of 11], 1971 -- 1972; MS177.001.044.00003 (Box 44)
  - Correspondence to and from Uruguay, 1971-72 [2 of 11], 1971 -- 1972; MS177.001.044.00004 (Box 44)
  - Correspondence to and from Uruguay, 1971-72 [3 of 11], 1971 -- 1972; MS177.001.044.00005 (Box 44)
  - Correspondence to and from Uruguay, 1971-72 [4 of 11], 1971 -- 1972; MS177.001.044.00006 (Box 44)
  - Correspondence to and from Uruguay, 1971-72 [5 of 11], 1971 -- 1972; MS177.001.044.00007 (Box 44)
  - Correspondence to and from Uruguay, 1971-72 [6 of 11], 1971 -- 1972; MS177.001.044.00008 (Box 44)
  - Correspondence to and from Uruguay, 1971-72 [7 of 11], 1971 -- 1972; MS177.001.044.00009 (Box 44)
  - Correspondence to and from Uruguay, 1971-72 [8 of 11], 1971 -- 1972; MS177.001.044.00010 (Box 44)
  - Correspondence to and from Uruguay, 1971-72 [9 of 11], 1971 -- 1972; MS177.001.044.00011 (Box 44)
  - Correspondence to and from Uruguay, 1971-72 [10 of 11], 1971 -- 1972; MS177.001.044.00012 (Box 44)
  - Correspondence to and from Uruguay, 1971-72 [11 of 11], 1971 -- 1972; MS177.001.044.00013 (Box 44)
  - [Notebooks and mementos from Uruguay], 1972; MS177.001.044.00014 (Box 44)
  - [Mementos from travel in South America], 1972; MS177.001.044.00015 (Box 44)
  - Letters from Uruguay since summer 72 [1 of 4], 1972 -- 1973; MS177.001.044.00016 (Box 44)
  - Letters from Uruguay since summer 72 [2 of 4], 1972 -- 1973; MS177.001.044.00017 (Box 44)
  - Letters from Uruguay since summer 72 [3 of 4], 1972 -- 1973; MS177.001.044.00018 (Box 44)
  - Letters from Uruguay since summer 72 [4 of 4], 1972 -- 1973; MS177.001.044.00019 (Box 44)
  - [Journal, including Uruguay clippings, letters from Uruguay, diary and class notes], 1973 -- 1974; MS177.001.044.00020 (Box 44)
  - [Writings], 1972; MS177.001.045.00001 (Box 45)
  - [Letters from Wendy], 1972; MS177.001.045.00002 (Box 45)
  - [Letters from Mike Schwager, 1 of 2], 1973; MS177.001.045.00003 (Box 45)
  - [Letters from Mike Schwager, 2 of 2], 1973; MS177.001.045.00004 (Box 45)
  - [Group photograph], 1975; MS177.001.045.00005 (Box 45)
  - [Course papers, correspondence and music programs from Temple University], 1972 -- 1976; MS177.001.045.00006 (Box 45)
  - Zaccardo, Patricia opera, 1976; MS177.001.045.00007 (Box 45)
  - La Voz de los Uros [newsletter from Peru], 1977; MS177.001.045.00008 (Box MS177 Shared 2)
  - [Address and notebooks], 1977; MS177.001.045.00009 (Box 45)
  - [Correspondence to Ellen in Pennsylvania, 1 of 2], 1976 -- 1978; MS177.001.045.00010 (Box 45)
  - [Correspondence to Ellen in Pennsylvania, 2 of 2], 1976 -- 1978; MS177.001.045.00011 (Box 45)
  - Law and anthropology, Bryn Mawr, 1977; MS177.001.045.00012 (Box 45)
  - [Bryn Mawr college commencement programs and official correspondence], 1976 -- 1978; MS177.001.045.00013 (Box 45)
  - [Notebook, mementos and correspondence from Uruguay], 1978; MS177.001.045.00014 (Box 45)
  - [Correspondence], 1979; MS177.001.045.00015 (Box 45)
  - [Diary and other writings], 1980 -- 1981; MS177.001.045.00016 (Box 45)
  - [Diary], 1981; MS177.001.045.00017 (Box 45)
  - [Servas travel to Europe], 1982; MS177.001.045.00018 (Box 45)
  - [Passports and other identification cards], 1971 -- 1983; MS177.001.045.00019 (Box 45)
  - [Correspondence regarding Papua New Guinea and other projects], 1982 -- 1985; MS177.001.045.00020 (Box 45)
  - [Glenn Randall and Ellen Lutz notebook from Papua New Guinea trip], 1983; MS177.001.045.00021 (Box 45)
  - [Loose personal writings], 1983; MS177.001.045.00022 (Box 45)
  - Law of the Bible and Talmud [UC Berkeley], 1981 -- 1982; MS177.001.045.00023 (Box 45)
  - ISP qual. exam notes [UC Berkeley], 1982 -- 1983; MS177.001.045.00024 (Box 45)
  - R. Unger [paper by Ellen], 1983; MS177.001.045.00025 (Box 45)
  - EL law school transcript, 1985; MS177.001.045.00026 (Box 45)
  - Law and anthropology: Berkeley, 1984; MS177.001.045.00027 (Box 45)
  - L. Nader, A. Sursock, Anthropology and Justice, 1984; MS177.001.045.00028 (Box 45)
  - [UC Berkeley - Boalt / Harvard exchange program application and acceptance letters], 1984; MS177.001.045.00029 (Box 45)
  - [Correspondence from Papua New Guinea], 1984; MS177.001.045.00030 (Box 45)
  - [Correspondence from Uruguay, Chile and Peru], 1984 -- 1986; MS177.001.045.00031 (Box 45)
  - [Loose correspondence, 1 of 6], 1980 -- 1986; MS177.001.046.00001 (Box 46)
  - [Loose correspondence, 2 of 6], 1980 -- 1986; MS177.001.046.00002 (Box 46)
  - [Loose correspondence, 3 of 6], 1980 -- 1986; MS177.001.046.00003 (Box 46)
  - [Loose correspondence, 4 of 6], 1980 -- 1986; MS177.001.046.00004 (Box 46)
  - [Loose correspondence, 5 of 6], 1980 -- 1986; MS177.001.046.00005 (Box 46)
  - [Loose correspondence, 6 of 6], 1980 -- 1986; MS177.001.046.00006 (Box 46)
  - In re: religion, 1995; MS177.001.046.00007 (Box 46)
  - Karina [in memoriam], 1995; MS177.001.046.00008 (Box 46)
  - Frank Newman in memoriam, 1996; MS177.001.046.00009 (Box 46)
  - Amy Shogan [recommendation], 1997; MS177.001.046.00010 (Box 46)
    75 years from the date of creation.
  - [Family photographs], 1997; MS177.001.046.00011 (Box 46)
  - [Correspondence with cousin, Dave], 2000; MS177.001.046.00012 (Box 46)
  - [Daily activity notes], 2000; MS177.001.046.00013 (Box 46)
  - [Rough board game design], 2001; MS177.001.046.00014 (Box 46)
  - [Letter from father regarding location of old Lutz family farm], 2001; MS177.001.046.00015 (Box 46)
  - [Political song], 2001; MS177.001.046.00016 (Box 46)
  - [Letter regarding Northern Ireland shooting incident], 2003; MS177.001.046.00017 (Box 46)
  - Open Society Justice Initiative job [1 of 2], 2003; MS177.001.046.00018 (Box 46)
  - Open Society Justice Initiative job [2 of 2], 2003; MS177.001.046.00019 (Box 46)
  - Job applications, 2003 -- 2004; MS177.001.046.00020 (Box 46)
  - [Glenn Randall's ELISA study, 1 of 7], 1983; MS177.001.046.00021 (Box 46)
  - [Glenn Randall's ELISA study, 2 of 7], 1983; MS177.001.046.00022 (Box 46)
  - [Glenn Randall's ELISA study, 3 of 7], 1983; MS177.001.046.00023 (Box 46)
  - [Glenn Randall's ELISA study, 4 of 7], 1983; MS177.001.046.00024 (Box 46)
  - [Glenn Randall's ELISA study, 5 of 7], 1981; MS177.001.046.00025 (Box 46)
  - [Glenn Randall's ELISA study, 6 of 7], 1981; MS177.001.046.00026 (Box 46)
  - [Glenn Randall's ELISA study, 7 of 7], 1980; MS177.001.046.00027 (Box 46)
  - Notebooks, 1971; MS177.001.047.00001 (Box MS177 Shared 4)
  - Diaries from Uruguay, numbers 1-2, 1971 -- 1972; MS177.001.047.00002 (Box MS177 Shared 4)
  - Diaries from Uruguay, numbers 3-4, 1972; MS177.001.047.00003 (Box MS177 Shared 4)
  - Diary from Uruguay, number 5, 1972; MS177.001.047.00004 (Box MS177 Shared 4)
  - South America I and II, 1972; MS177.001.047.00005 (Box MS177 Shared 4)
  - College and high school diplomas, 1972 -- 1976; MS177.001.047.00006 (Box MS177 Shared 4)
  - Resume, 1976; MS177.001.047.00007 (Box MS177 Shared 4)
  - Contracts and Marriage: A Cross-Cultural Comparison Master's thesis, 1978; MS177.001.047.00008 (Box MS177 Shared 4)
  - South and Latin American travel diaries, 1 of 2, 1978 -- 1985; MS177.001.047.00009 (Box MS177 Shared 4)
    These are diaries from travel in Uruguay, Ecuador, Peru, Bolivia, Paraguay, Argentina and Brazil.
  - South and Latin American travel diaries, 2 of 2, 1978 -- 1985; MS177.001.047.00010 (Box MS177 Shared 4)
  - Dawson, 1985; MS177.001.047.00011 (Box MS177 Shared 2)
  - University of California Juris Doctor degree, 1985; MS177.001.047.00012 (Box Large Map Case 2 Drawer 3)
  - Martina 1 of 2, 1993 -- 1997; MS177.001.047.00013 (Box MS177 Shared 4)
  - Martina 2 of 2, 1994; MS177.001.047.00014 (Box MS177 Shared 4)
  - Miscellaneous personal correspondence 1 of 2, 1994 -- 1997; MS177.001.047.00015 (Box MS177 Shared 4)
  - Miscellaneous personal correspondence 2 of 2, 1994 -- 1997; MS177.001.047.00016 (Box MS177 Shared 4)
  - Postcards, 1 of 2, 1977 -- 1991; MS177.001.047.00017 (Box MS177 Shared 4)
  - Postcards, 2 of 2, 1966 -- 2004; MS177.001.047.00018 (Box MS177 Shared 4)
  - Family correspondence and Temple commencement material, 1965 -- 2000; MS177.001.047.00019 (Box MS177 Shared 4)
  - Personal files from external hard drive, 2009; MS177.001.047.00024
  - OPENSPACE includes OSPC, WCLT, 1998-06-05; MS177.001.047.00025
  - OSI job, Cultural Survival job, misc, 2003; MS177.001.047.00026
  - Picnic Pics, Glen, 2002-04-07; MS177.001.047.00027
- Research materials and field investigations regarding victims of the military juntas in Uruguay, Argentina and Chile, 1960 -- 1986; 1976 -- 1985; MS177.002; 2.95 Linear Feet; 1 Audiovisual Object(s); 5 Digital Object(s)
  This series contains correspondence, reports and project files regarding torture and human rights violations by the military junta in Uruguay, as well as newspapers, pamphlets and other literature regarding political prisoners and abuses by military Juntas from Chile, Argentina and Uruguay. The material dates from 1978 through 1985, and roughly a third of it is in Spanish. About half of the material is labeled "Uruguay" and dates from Lutz's time working as Amnesty International's Campaign Assistant for Latin America in Washington, D.C. (1978-1979) and then as their Western Regional Organizer in San Francisco (1980-1982). In a letter dated December 10, 1980 she describes herself as having "taken responsibility for administering much of AIUSA's work on that country [Uruguay] during the past two years." (see 001:00010, Uruguay – "AI Correspondence" folder) The other half of the material documents Lutz's travels in the summer of 1985 to Argentina, Uruguay and Chile, where she researched the trial of members of Argentina's former military government and government assistance for victims of human rights violations (see 002:00016, letter to Margo Picken). Included are two cassette tapes of interviews with Ester Kaufman and Marcelo Parrilli, an Argentine human rights lawyer and founding member of the Center for Legal Social Studies (CELS).
  This series is arranged as received, in rough chronological order, with minor adjustments to incorporate loose material.
  - La Mañana, 1972-04-15; MS177.002.001.00001 (Box Large Map Case 2 Drawer 3)
    This folder is located in map case drawer.
  - [Tupamaros], 1971 -- 1973; MS177.002.001.00002 (Box 1)
  - [Newspaper clippings and Amnesty International memos regarding torture and AI's future work in Uruguay], 1976 -- 1977; MS177.002.001.00003 (Box 1)
  - Mexico section, 1976 -- 1978; MS177.002.001.00004 (Box 1)
  - [Notebooks containing translations of letters, novel outlines, to do lists and contacts], 1978 -- 1979; MS177.002.001.00005 (Box 1)
    This date is approximate.
  - Uruguay case sheets, 1978 -- 1979; MS177.002.001.00006 (Box 1)
  - Uruguay Special Action material, 1979; MS177.002.001.00007 (Box 1)
  - Political Imprisonment in Uruguay, Amnesty International, 1979; MS177.002.001.00008 (Box 1)
  - Uruguay: Urgent action & amnesty action appeals, letters, response & translations, 1978 -- 1979; MS177.002.001.00009 (Box 1)
  - Uruguay - AI correspondence, 1979 -- 1981; MS177.002.001.00010 (Box 1)
  - Uruguay Special Action, Fall 80, 1980; MS177.002.001.00011 (Box 1)
  - Uruguay - Press clippings, 1980 -- 1981; MS177.002.001.00012 (Box 1)
  - Pacheco Areco, Uruguay ambassador to U.S., 1980; MS177.002.001.00013 (Box 1)
  - Adolf Saenz (Mitrione's predecessor), 1980; MS177.002.001.00014 (Box 1)
  - SIJAU - Testimony of Garcia Rivas, 1980; MS177.002.001.00015 (Box 1)
  - Uruguay: Sara Ibarburu, 'mal de hodgkins', 1980; MS177.002.001.00016 (Box 1)
  - Uruguay: Rabbi Rosenthal's visit 5/80, 1980; MS177.002.001.00017 (Box 1)
  - Uruguay: Complaint to IACHR re: Celiberti et. al., 1979; MS177.002.001.00018 (Box 1)
  - State Dept. H.R. report / response, 1980; MS177.002.001.00019 (Box 1)
  - Materials sent to adoption groups w/ Uruguayan doc's., 1979; MS177.002.001.00020 (Box 1)
  - Uruguay: Liber Seregni, 1980; MS177.002.001.00021 (Box 1)
  - Uruguay: Francisco Laurenzo-Pons, 1980 -- 1981; MS177.002.001.00022 (Box 1)
  - Jose Luis Massera, 1979 -- 1980; MS177.002.001.00023 (Box 1)
  - Uruguay: Persecution of scientists, 1980; MS177.002.001.00024 (Box 1)
  - Uruguay: 'Desparacidos', 1979; MS177.002.001.00025 (Box 1)
  - Uruguay 1980-81 misc., 1980 -- 1981; MS177.002.001.00026 (Box 1)
  - Uruguay: Oldies but goodies, 1975 -- 1978; MS177.002.001.00027 (Box 1)
  - Uruguay seminar notes, May 1980, MS177.002.001.00028 (Box 1)
  - Uruguay - Las Bases Constitucionales, 1980; MS177.002.001.00029 (Box 1)
  - Uruguay: Bibliography, 1960 -- 1981; MS177.002.001.00030 (Box 1)
  - Uruguay: W.D.L.A. info., 1978 -- 1981; MS177.002.001.00031 (Box 1)
  - Uruguay - AI material, 1981; MS177.002.001.00032 (Box 1)
  - Uruguay - Misc. information, 1977 -- 1981; MS177.002.001.00033 (Box 1)
  - [Reports, newsletters and press releases regarding human rights in Uruguay, 1 of 6], 1979 -- 1981; MS177.002.001.00034 (Box 1)
  - [Reports, newsletters and press releases regarding human rights in Uruguay, 2 of 6], 1976 -- 1980; MS177.002.001.00035 (Box 1)
  - [Reports, newsletters and press releases regarding human rights in Uruguay, 3 of 6], 1976 -- 1980; MS177.002.001.00036 (Box 1)
  - [Introduction to Amnesty International speech], 1982; MS177.002.001.00037 (Box 1)
  - [Reports, newsletters and press releases regarding human rights in Uruguay, 4 of 6], 1976 -- 1980; MS177.002.002.00001 (Box 2)
  - [Reports, newsletters and press releases regarding human rights in Uruguay, 5 of 6], 1979 -- 1980; MS177.002.002.00002 (Box 2)
  - [Reports, newsletters and press releases regarding human rights in Uruguay, 6 of 6], 1977 -- 1980; MS177.002.002.00003 (Box 2)
  - Uruguay, 1981 -- 1984; MS177.002.002.00004 (Box 2)
  - Uruguay: Co-group newsletter [1 of 4], 1984 -- 1985; MS177.002.002.00005 (Box 2)
  - Uruguay: Co-group newsletter [2 of 4], 1981 -- 1984; MS177.002.002.00006 (Box 2)
  - Uruguay: Co-group newsletter [3 of 4], 1981 -- 1983; MS177.002.002.00007 (Box 2)
  - Uruguay: Co-group newsletter [4 of 4], 1982 -- 1984; MS177.002.002.00008 (Box 2)
  - Arrest of Wilson & Juan F. A. [Ferreira Aldunate], 1984; MS177.002.002.00009 (Box 2)